I used Yosemite for the installation process, but it should work with later versions.
For Mac OS X, we will install Apple's version of Git
provided by the command line developer tools, TextMate 2, and finally P4Merge.
Installing Git on the Mac has become super simple. Open your terminal program,
and simply type "git", that's "g-i-t"; space; version, then press enter.
If Git responds with a version number, then Git is already installed. Otherwise,
your system will prompt you for whether or not you want to install the command line
developer tools, or Xcode. If you plan to use Xcode, then choose that option;
but, not everyone needs or wants Xcode, and Xcode is a huge download
just for a handful of command line utilities, including Git. I'll assume that you
just want to install the command line developer tools; just follow the install prompts
as needed, and accept any defaults. Once that's done, test it out by typing:
"git version", then press enter. If Git responds with a version number,
then you are good to go. Before moving on, I like to set up the minimal configuration
required for any significant work in Git. Git needs your name and email address
before we can do very much with it, so, let's set that up now; with your terminal
still open, type the following commands "git config --global user.name", space,
and then, in double quotes, specify your name; press enter. Then next type
"git config --global user.email", space, and then in double quotes
specify your email address. Once you've done that, press enter.
Now, with Git installed and configured, we can proceed to installing a decent text editor.
While technically an optional step, the default text editor for Mac OSX is the rather
limited TextEdit. Also, the default editor for Git is the command line centric Vi editor.
Personally, I'm not a fan of either; instead, I like to use TextMate 2, and configure it
to work seamlessly with Git. To start, download the installer for TextMate 2
from their website at "macromates.com". Click on the TextMate 2.0 installer;
don't worry if it says beta, or something like that, it's been very stable for me so far.
You will be given an archive; just expand the archive file, which will contain the
TextMate.app. Drag the TextMate.app into your applications folder, and, that's
basically the install process. Next, open TextMate 2, and then go to preferences,
and install the command line support, which will setup the "mate" command,
that will be available from the terminal. Now that we have TextMate 2 installed,
let's make it our default editor for Git; we do that with Git's "config" command.
Type "git config --global core.editor", space, and then in double quotes the command
"mate -w", now press enter. Now that we've done that, let's test it out by asking Git
to open its own config file, with the default editor, with this command:
"git config --global -e", then press enter. If TextMate loads
the global ".gitconfig" file, then the Git integration was successful.
Finally, the last tool for this installation section is P4Merge for Mac,
which is a visual comparison and merge resolution tool that integrates well with Git.
Technically, we don't need to do this untill we get to the part of the course
regarding comparing, branching, and merging,
and only if you want to use a graphical tool for comparing and resolving conflicts.
To start off, go to Perforce's website at "perforce.com", then click on the downloads page.
Fair warning, Perforce frequently updates their site,
so the exact path to the downloads page and the P4Merge installer may change.
Once on the downloads page, go to the Helix clients, and find
"P4Merge: Visual Merge Tool", or something similar to that.
Choose the correct installer that best matches your operating system,
and then click the download button. If prompted, you may skip the registration,
which then should start the download of the actual installer image for P4Merge.
Once downloaded, run the installer image; only install the P4Merge client and nothing else.
Now, let's integrate P4Merge with Git; you'll need to know where
P4Merge is installed on your system, which is normally under "/Applications".
With the next series of commands, you may need to modify them slightly to fit on your system.
Let's start by setting up P4Merge as our graphical compare tool with Git.
Type "git config --global diff.tool p4merge", press enter.
Then type "git config --global difftool.p4merge.path",
space, then, within double quotes, the full path to the P4Merge executable.
Once you've type that out or pasted it in, double check and then press enter.
Finally, type "git config --global difftool.prompt false", then press enter.
Now, let's configure P4Merge as the graphical mergetool;
type "git config --global merge.tool p4merge", press enter.
Then, next, type "git config --global mergetool.p4merge.path",
space, and then in double quotes, the full path to the P4Merge executable.
Double check that, and then press enter.
Finally, type "git config --global mergetool.prompt false", then press enter.
If you experience any problems, check out the install instructions in the next lecture.